A Finding Aid to the Robert Pincus-Witten Papers, 1942-2017, bulk 1962-2005, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1953-2016; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Box 4-5
  - Drafts, "The New Irascibles: A Portfolio of Six Photographs by Timothy Greenfield-Sanders", 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Drafts, "Theory Weary", circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Drafts, "Thirty Years of Artforum: The Page was My Party", circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Drafts, "Unpublished Entries" and "Work in Progress Entries", 1977-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Drafts, Unpublished Talks on Criticism, 1978-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Graduate and Undergraduate Essays and Notes, 1953-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Graduate and Undergraduate Essays and Notes, circa 1956-1970, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Graduate Essays and Notes, 1957-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Graduate Essays and Notes, 1958-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lectures, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key; 5 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Master's Thesis Drafts, "Surrealistic Currents in the Symbolist Period", circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Notes, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Notes, 1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Notes, circa 1980s-circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Poem, "The Wit and Wisdom of Larry Gagosian", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Political and Critical Views, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Artist Files, 1950-2016; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.6 Linear feet Box 5-7
  Artist files maintain Pincus-Witten's original arrangement and date from 1950-2016. Materials consist of correspondence including printed emails, postcards, letters and facsimiles; exhibition catalogs, announcements, checklists, posters, and invitations; artists CVs; clippings including reviews of the artists work; draft essays about the artists and their work; lists of works; notes; periodicals; draft presentations; greeting cards; brochures; thank you notes; bibliographies; notecards; photocopies of Pincus-Witten's journal entries related to the artists; invoices; copies of certificates of insurance; color and black and white photographs, negatives, and slides; press releases; travel documentation including itineraries; printed internet articles; interview transcripts; newsletters; holiday cards; a draft eulogy Pincus-Witten wrote for Corice C. Arman; memorial programs and announcements; exhibition checklists and posters; and a birth announcement. Artists of note include Christo and Jean-Claude, Eva Hesse, Liza Lou, Cindy Nemser, Richard Serra, Cy Twombly, and Rose Cabot. Also included is a CD-R from Rose Cabot's "The Marks Project."
  - Corice C. Arman, 2005-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Mike Bidlo, 1977-2003, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mike Bidlo, 1977-2003, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Scott Burton, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Christo and Jeanne-Claude, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - James Collins, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - James Collins, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - James Collins, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Eva Hesse, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Eva Hesse, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Eva Hesse, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Eva Hesse, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Eva Hesse, 1960-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Ray Johnson, 1969-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Gary Komarin, 1977-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Daniel Lang, 1969-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Liza Lou, 1996-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Liza Lou, 1996-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Cindy Nemser, 1971-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Cindy Nemser, 1971-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Richard Serra/Gary Stephan, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Richard Serra, 1973-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Charles Sheeler/Paul Strand, 1980-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Susan Sontag, 1992-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Sacha Sosno, 1961-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Sacha Sosno, 1961-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Sacha Sosno, 1961-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Starn Twins, 1986-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Starn Twins, 1986-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Frank Stella, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cy Twombly, 1994-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cy Twombly, 1994-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Cy Twombly, 1994-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Rose Cabot, 1966-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rose Cabot, 1966-2015; Archival Resource Key; Includes one CD-R (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Rose Cabot, 1966-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Leo Castelli, 1950-1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Leo Castelli, 1950-1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Professional Files, 1959-2009; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet Box 7-8
  Professional files document different aspects of Pincus-Witten's career from 1973-2009. The Gagosian Gallery files date from 1989-1993 and include daily logs in memorandum format and addressed to Larry Gagosian, correspondence, lists of catalogs published by the gallery, invoices, facsimiles, transcribed journal entries, clippings, exhibition catalogs, draft essays, press releases, meeting notes, Yves Klein litigation regarding a possible fake, and a faxed photograph of Pincus-Witten and Leon Hecht. Other materials include documentation related to Pincus-Witten's travels to the 11th Annual International Sculpture Conference in 1980; a 2007 Adi Foundation Symposium in Jerusalem; the 1997 Cunard Cruise to Hamburg where Pincus-Witten gave a series of lectures; a 1995 Paris flight itinerary; an International Art Press Group to Israel in 1986; and color photographs of a trip to Washington, D.C. in circa 1990 and photographs from Israel trips taken between 1975 and 1977. There is a folder from Omni Art Co. that includes correspondence, invoices, email printouts, exhibition announcements, invitations, and a photocopied group photo; correspondence related to a post-minimalism exhibition Pincus-Witten wanted to curate at MoMA that includes correspondence between himself and Bill (William) Rubin from 1973, where they politely discuss a disagreement regarding what defines modern art; and a draft MoMA PS1 Deputy Director contract from 2003. Audiovisual materials in this series include audio recordings on sound cassettes of lectures and panel discussions featuring Pincus-Witten, a Marcel Duchamp interview by Richard Hamilton; and two sound reels of panel discussions with Pincus-Witten including "Disintegration of Minimalism" at the High Museum in 1973. Also included are photographs of Iris Clert artwork, Ray Johnson collages, Jeff Koon's "Pink Panther" in a crate, and 12 folders of reference photographs depicting artist artworks and installations including artists such as Albert Ryder, George Segal, Henry O. Tanner, Joshua Neustein, Eva Hesse, Hector Guimard, Rachel Lalique, Giorgio de Chirico, Bruce D. Kurt, Margaret Wharton, and others.
  - 11th Annual International Sculpture Conference, June 4-7, 1980, Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Adi Foundation Symposium in Jerusalem, "Jewish Expression in the Visual Arts", 2006-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Artforum, 1973-1976, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Color Photographs from a Washington, D.C. Trip, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Color Polaroid of Jeff Koon's "Pink Panther" in a Crate, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Cunard Cruise to Hamburg, "Baltic Voyager", 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Ephemera; Invoices; and Correspondence re Book Publishing and Reproduction Rights, 1983-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Disintegration of Minimalism, Walter Hill Auditorium: The High Museum: Atlanta, Georgia, April 12, 1973, Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Forum Roundtable, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Gagosian Gallery, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Gagosian Gallery [1], 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Gagosian Gallery [2], 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Gagosian Gallery [3], 1989-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Gagosian Gallery [4], 1989-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Gagosian Gallery: Yves Klein Litigation, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - International Art Press Group Trip to Israel, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Marcel Duchamp Interviewed by Richard Hamilton, 1959; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - MoMA Panel, "What Happened to the 80s?", 1997; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - MoMA P.S.1 Draft Deputy Director Contract, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Paris Flight Itinerary, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Photographs from Israel Trips, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, Iris Clert Artwork, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Ray Johnson Collages, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Post Minimalism Exhibition, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Recurring Regionalism Panel, 1979; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cartridges (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12)
    (includes artwork by Roger Brown, Jean Delville, Bruce D. Kurt, and Jan Toorop)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13)
    (includes artwork by Hector Guimard and Rene Lalique)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 14)
    (includes artwork by Giorgio de Chirico)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1970-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15)
    (includes artwork by Eva Hesse and Rene Lalique)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1973-circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16)
    (includes artwork by Rupert Carabin and Ferdinand Holder)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, circa 1968-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17)
    (includes artwork by Eva Hesse, Allan Kaprow, and Margaret Wharton)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, Albert Ryder, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, George Segal, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, Henry O. Tanner, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, Joshua Neustein, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, Medallions, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Reference Photographs: Artwork and Installations, Targets, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Research Materials, 1968-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Video Panel Discussion with Pincus-Witten, 10/3/74, 1974; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Teaching Files, circa 1970s-1996; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 8-9
  Teaching files include student correspondence regarding thesis projects and references; handwritten lecture notes with slide descriptions and photocopies of slides from the 1970s; student artwork slides from 1990; a copy of a circa 1989 early modern art class final; annotated draft lectures; clippings; notes for a twentieth century art and theory course; bibliographies; essays written by Pincus-Witten; Sotheby's American Arts course materials from 1988-1989 including faculty lists, teaching assignments, correspondence, meeting minutes, and a copy of Southeby's grading system; CUNY slide lists for lectures; a John Baldessari exhibition checklist; and a description of CUNY's art history doctoral program with proposed curriculum.
  - Art History, Faculty Activities, Publications, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Early Modern Final, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Lecture Notes and Lecture Slide Descriptions, 1971-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Lecture Notes and Lecture Slide Descriptions, 1971-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Lecture Notes and Lecture Slide Descriptions, 1971-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lecture Notes and Lecture Slide Descriptions, 1975-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, Lecture Slide Descriptions, and Lecture Notes, 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Sotheby's Educational Studies, American Arts Courses, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Student Artworks Slides: John Gaspar, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Student Correspondence, 1986, 1990-1996; Archival Resource Key; Includes one 5 1/4" floppy disc (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Twentieth Century Art and Theory Notes, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Printed Material, 1962-2017; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.95 Linear feet Box 9-10
  Printed material includes wedding invitation packets and programs; opera, theater, and orchestra programs from 1977-2001; gallery, museum, hotel, cruise, and historic site pamphlets; clippings; event menus; artist statements from 2000-2004; blank postcards; event tickets from 1986-1997; exhibition announcements, invitations, and posters; cruise passenger lists; newsletters; clippings related to artists, exhibitions, and performances; memorial service announcements and programs; copies of "Iris Times" and other newsletters; press releases; printed bibliographies; lecture, symposium, and course flyers from 1973-1982; an undated checklist proposal; 2008 and undated art of sale catalogs; photocopies of exhibition catalogs; press releases from 1980-2009; and art ephemera cards.
  - Artist Statements, 2000-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Blank Postcards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Cards, Art Ephemera, 1992-1997, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Catalogs: Art of Sale, 2008, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Checklist Proposal, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, Iris Times Newsletter, 1962-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1998-2017, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, Iris Times, 1962-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, Weegee, 1998-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Event Menus, 1996-2000, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1970-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1994-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1995-2015, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Invitations, 1979-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Invitations, 1996-2008, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Posters, 1970-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Lectures, Symposiums, Courses, 1973-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Memorial Cards and Programs, 1981-1997, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Newsletters, 1952-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Pamphlets-Gallery, Museum, Hotel, Cruise, Historic Sites, 1964-2001, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Press Releases, 1980-2009, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Programs, Events, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Programs, Events, 1981-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Programs, Events, 1981-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Programs, Events, 1981-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Programs, Events, 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Programs, Events, 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Programs, Events, 1996-2001, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Programs, Weddings, 1998-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Tickets, 1986-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Windsor Bibliography, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Artwork, 1959-1996; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.25 Linear feet Box 10
  Artwork includes pencil, ink, and watercolor sketches and sketchbooks created by Robert Pincus-Witten in the late 1950s and early 1990s. Most of the sketches are dated from the late 1990s, and the early 1990s sketches include pencil drawings of Leon Hecht.
  - Sketchbooks, 1959-1960, 1994-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbooks, 1994, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbooks, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Sketches, 1994, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Unidentified Born Digital Materials, circa 1980s-circa 2000s; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 10
  Unidentified Born Digital Materials include thirty-one 5.25 floppy disk(s). Labels indicate files contained on the discs may be writings by Pincus-Witten. Some software disk(s) are included.
  - Born-Digital Media, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key; 15 Floppy discs (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Born-Digital Media, circa 1989-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 16 Floppy discs (Box 10, Folder 14)